Guide to the George Mann Richardson Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George Mann Richardson papers
1860-1971
SC0285
Richardson, George Mann, 1863-
1.5 Linear feet
Correspondence, photographs, legal papers, albums and biographical material of George Mann Richardson, his wife Margaret Watson, their sons Alan and Remond, and Watson family relatives. Correspondence includes a family letter describing a trip to Colorado and New Mexico, 1887; letters by George, 1894, and Margaret, 1896, describing hiking trips in the Sierras (what is now Kings Canyon and Sequoia National Parks), and correspondence of Alan Richardson, 1918-1957, including one letter from Lou Henry Hoover. Photographs, 1898-1924, include early views of the Stanford campus, damage from the 1906 earthquake, the Richardson house on campus, family members, beach and mountain scenes, and Remond W. Richardson in his military unit in Texas, 1916-1917. There is a scrapbook kept by Remond W. Richardson, 1910-1923, containing programs, newsletters, clippings, and other items pertaining to his school and military activities; and a scrapbook kept by George Mann Richardson, 1881-1890, containing programs, clippings, tickets, ribbons, newsletters, and other items largely pertaining to Lehigh University athletic events and Psi Upsilon fraternity matters. The collection also includes a diary kept by George C. Richardson, 1860; letters by Robert Watson, 1885-1926; letters of Esther E. Watson, primarily on the death of her father William T. Watson, 1926; and other materials pertaining to the Watson family.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Jeanne Richardson Musto, 1982.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of Organic Chemistry at Stanford (1891-1902). Richardson, born in Springfield, Ohio 3 October 1863, obtained his A.B. in Chemistry from Lehigh University (1886) and his Ph. D. in Chemistry from John Hopkins University (1891). He died in 1902.
Description of the Collection
Correspondence, photographs, legal papers, albums and biographical material of George Mann Richardson, his wife Margaret Watson, their sons Alan and Remond, and Watson family relatives. Correspondence includes a family letter describing a trip to Colorado and New Mexico, 1887; letters by George, 1894, and Margaret, 1896, describing hiking trips in the Sierras (what is now Kings Canyon and Sequoia National Parks), and correspondence of Alan Richardson, 1918-1957, including one letter from Lou Henry Hoover. Photographs, 1898-1924, include early views of the Stanford campus, damage from the 1906 earthquake, the Richardson house on campus, family members, beach and mountain scenes, and Remond W. Richardson in his military unit in Texas, 1916-1917. There is a scrapbook kept by Remond W. Richardson, 1910-1923, containing programs, newsletters, clippings, and other items pertaining to his school and military activities; and a scrapbook kept by George Mann Richardson, 1881-1890, containing programs, clippings, tickets, ribbons, newsletters, and other items largely pertaining to Lehigh University athletic events and Psi Upsilon fraternity matters. The collection also includes a diary kept by George C. Richardson, 1860; letters by Robert Watson, 1885-1926; letters of Esther E. Watson, primarily on the death of her father William T. Watson, 1926; and other materials pertaining to the Watson family.
Access Terms
Hoover, Lou Henry, 1874-1944.; Richardson, Alan.; Richardson, George C.; Richardson, George Mann, 1863-; Richardson, Margaret.; Richardson, Remond W.; Watson family.; Watson, Esther E.; Watson, Robert.; Albums.; Hiking --Sierra Nevada Mountains (Calif. and Nev.).; Kings Canyon National Park (Calif.).; Photoprints.; Sequoia National Park (Calif.).
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Snapshots and photographs of GMR, family and campus (5) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Portraits of GMR (5) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Portrait – Mrs. GMR (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Snapshots – children (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photos – house (Stanford?) (6) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Snapshots – GMR bicycle trip (3) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photo – four men in the woods (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photo – schoolchildren (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photos – campus shots (5) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newsclipping, obituary (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Richardson family correspondence, 1881-1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - ephemera
    - biography of GMR (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "The Gospel of Work" by GMR (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Theta Xi publication "TAU-LK" (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Citizenship Certificate (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - San Francisco Memorial Souvenir of 1906 earthquake (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Poems (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Birth proof for Alan Campbell Richardson (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Program of the Chit Chat Club (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Silver Quill awards dinner program (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1890 conferring of degrees, Johns Hopkins University (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Four photograph albums (Box 2)
  - One photograph album (Box 3)
  - Douglas, Howard Grey. Library of Congress [reproductions of architectural and mural decorations] (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Holiday cards, 1923-37 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous family letters, ca. 1971-73 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous items
    - Clipping re S. U. fencing team (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Milton P. Duffy Testimonial Dinner program, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Poem (printed) by Elizabeth York Case, 1907 with note by MWR on reverse (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Copy of map of Oregon Territory (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Harrison, Ross Granville, On the Occurrence of Tails in Man, with a Description of the Case Reported by Dr. Watson." 1901 reprint (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - The Phonographic World, Aug. 1890 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Brochure [possibly pages from a book] on Westminster Abbey (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Negatives of coastal scenes (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Negative of a family group, ca. 1900 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Negatives of family groups and an individual (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Negatives of a seaside or lakeside town (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photographs: Bob and Will Watson, Lake Chelan, and relief map of California (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Postcards, 1905-1910 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Reik, Mary Watson, letters to Margaret, 1937 and undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Richardson, Alan C. – biographical materials, 1927, 1960-ca. 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Richardson, Alan C. – correspondence, 1911, 1924 and undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Richardson, Alan C. – patents, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Richardson, Alan C. and Marna C. – documents (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Richardson, George C., diary, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Richardson, George C., loose items from diary (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Richardson, George M., calling cards and train ticket (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Richardson, R. W., fishing license 1923, S. U. study list spring quarter 1920, and letter to Uncle Bob, 1912 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Richardson family documents – copies (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - San Antonio, Texas, souvenir, ca. 1916 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Swain, Robert E., letter to Alan Richardson, 1952 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Washington High School Cadets, programs, 1915-17; The Review, Central High School, Washington, DC, Feb. 1917 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Watercolor sketches, unsigned (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Watson, Doug, letters received on the death of his father, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Watson, Esther, letters to Doug, 1926, and other family letters, 1971 and undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Watson, Robert, letters to family, 1885-1926 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Watson, Robert C., clipping, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Watson, William T., obituary, 1926, and photograph (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Watson family, genealogy and miscellaneous items (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Photo album: family groups, scenic views, dogs (Box 5)
  - Original Kodak negative album [negatives removed and housed in box 4] (Box 5)
  - Memorabilia of G.M. Richardson, R. W. Richardson, and other unidentified family members; includes athletic and military pins and medals; GMR's leather card case; and NRA buttons (Box 6)
  - Album kept by G. M. Richardson, 1881-1890, containing programs, clippings, tickets, ribbons, newsletters, and other items largely pertaining to Lehigh University athletic events and Psi Upsilon fraternity matters (Box 7)